<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-03T11:59:10-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Notes on Littlewood’s ‘Large Numbers’ and Related Thoughts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/uuiate/2022/01/03/big-numbers-notes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Littlewood’s ‘Large Numbers’ and Related Thoughts" /><published>2022-01-03T08:28:12-06:00</published><updated>2022-01-03T08:28:12-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/uuiate/2022/01/03/big-numbers-notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/uuiate/2022/01/03/big-numbers-notes.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="coincidences--probabilities">Coincidences / Probabilities</h2>

<h3 id="will-west-case">Will West Case</h3>

<p>Littlewood writes:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Dorothy Sayers in Unpopular Opinions, cites the case of two negroes, each named Will West, confined simultaneously in Leavenworth Penitentiary, U.S.A. (in 1903), and with the same Bertillon measurements. (Is this really credible ?)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We estimate this probability, let $P$ be the probability that two people share the same facial features, Bertillon measurements and name. We have:</p>

\[P \approx \underbrace{\text{Prob(same body measurements)}}_{:=P_b} \; \cdot \;  \underbrace{\text{Prob(same name)}}_{:=P_n}\]

<h5 id="estimationg-p_n">Estimationg \(P_n\)</h5>

<p>Let \(n_1, n_2\) be the names of two arbitrary people. We have the crude approximation:</p>

\[P(n_1 = n_2) = \sum_{\text{names }n} P(n_1 = n) P(n_2 = n) = \sum_{\text{names } n} P(n)^2\]

<p>Using data from <a href="https://www.ssa.gov/OACT/babynames/">U.S. Social Security Adminbistration</a> and using the top 1000 names from the years 1880 and 2010 (assuming that 50% of births are male and 50% of births are female), we <a href="https://gist.github.com/epistemologist/12cff945e6b8c918055f5585fc373c7f">get estimates</a> of probabilities of 1.8% and 0.21% respectively. Assuming that choosing first names and last names are independent, we estimate that $ P_n \approx 10^{-2} \cdot 10^{-2} = 10^{-4} $</p>

<h5 id="estimating-p_b-and-p_f">Estimating \(P_b\) and \(P_f\)</h5>

<p>Littlewood mentions that the two Wests’ shared Bermillon measurements - these are a system of 11 different biometric measurements that were taken of prisoners as means of identification. In the original case, the measurements of the two Wests’ were <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120505160629/opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/05/01/whats-in-a-name-part-2/">not exactly the same, but remarkably similar</a>.</p>

<p>Bertillon <a href="https://rss.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/j.1740-9713.2014.00739.x">himself predicted</a> that the probability of two people sharing all 11 measurements was \(P_b \approx 1/4^{32} = 1/268435456\). However, <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs00414-015-1158-6">more recent studies</a> in forensic anthropometry place the probability of two people sharing 8 different body measurement traits at \(P_b \approx 10^{-20}\).</p>

<p>We therefore make the estimate \(P_b \approx 10^{-12}\) and therefore, \(P \approx 10^{-12} \cdot \cdot 10^{-4} = 10^{-16}\).</p>

<h5 id="wrapping-things-up">Wrapping Things Up</h5>

<p>We now calculate the probability that for any one person being incarcerated that they share the same features to someone in the same prison that they are being held similarly to the two Will Wests.</p>

<p>Assuming an average prison houses an average of <a href="https://www.americanjail.org/jail-statistics">250 inmates</a>, the probability that a person who is imprisoned meets their doppelganger in the same prison is \(p = 1 - (1-P)^{250}\).</p>

<p>Therefore, if $n$ people are incarcerated, we have that the probability that any one person will find their doppelganger is \(p' = 1 - (1-p)^n = 1 - (1-P)^{250n}\).
Considering that the U.S. made <a href="https://www.ojjdp.gov/ojstatbb/crime/ucr.asp?table_in=2">10 million arrests in 2019</a>, we estimate \(N \approx 5 \cdot 10^6\). We therefore have that:</p>

\[p' = 1 - (1-P)^{N} = 1 - \left( 1 - NP + \frac{N(N-1)}{2} P^2 - \cdots \right) = NP + O(P^2)\]

<p>Plugging in \(N = 250 \cdot 5 \cdot 10^6, P = 10^{-16}\), we get that $p’ \approx 10^{-7}$.</p>

<p>This probability is reasonable as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doppelg%C3%A4nger#Examples_in_real_life">various doppelgangers have been found in real life</a> and so we expect it to be within the realm of possibility.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="uuiate" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Coincidences / Probabilities]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/01/03/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2022-01-03T08:28:12-06:00</published><updated>2022-01-03T08:28:12-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/01/03/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/01/03/welcome-to-jekyll.html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ll find this post in your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_posts</code> directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll serve</code>, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</p>

<p>Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP</code></p>

<p>Where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR</code> is a four-digit number, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MONTH</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">DAY</code> are both two-digit numbers, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MARKUP</code> is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.</p>

<p>Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"Hi, </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
<span class="n">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'Tom'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="c1">#=&gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home">Jekyll docs</a> for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at <a href="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll’s GitHub repo</a>. If you have questions, you can ask them on <a href="https://talk.jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll Talk</a>.</p>

\[a^2 + b^2 = c^2\]]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated. Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format: YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP Where YEAR is a four-digit number, MONTH and DAY are both two-digit numbers, and MARKUP is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works. Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets: def print_hi(name) puts "Hi, #{name}" end print_hi('Tom') #=&gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT. Check out the Jekyll docs for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at Jekyll’s GitHub repo. If you have questions, you can ask them on Jekyll Talk. \[a^2 + b^2 = c^2\]]]></summary></entry></feed>